Guide to the Young People's Socialist League Records TAM.309
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Young People's Socialist League Records
1920-1960
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Young People's Socialist League
Baker, Zachary M.
TAM.309
0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box.
Box 1
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials donated by Zachary M. Baker, Librarian at the Jewish Public Library in Montreal, Canada, in 1983. The accession number associated with this gift is 1950.229.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Young People's Socialist League (YPSL) has been the name of the youth section of the Socialist Party USA (SP). It originated in New York City in 1907 as the Young People's Socialist Federation, however, by 1918 it became known as the YPSL (members were often referred to as Yipsels). In the 1930s, the majority of the YPSL membership sided with the Militant faction within the Socialist Party, led by Norman Thomas, against the more moderate "Old Guard" linked to the garment industry unions, the Rand School, and the SP's periodical, the New Leader, which withdrew from the SP in 1936 to form the Social Democratic Federation. In that same year, U.S. Trotskyists entered the SP and the YPSL en masse in an attempt to win them to their political program, and within the YPSL, they had considerable success. A number of Yipsels, such as sociologist Daniel Bell, would go on to become prominent intellectuals, in particular within the anti-communist left. The YPSL continued to exist, with some periodic mergers with other organizations and related name changes, into the 1980s, with Trotskyists, and former Trotskyists, playing an important role.
Scope and Content Note
The collection, which focuses on the Greater New York (City) and national organizations of the Young People's Socialist League, contains correspondence, minutes, reports including a proposed program by Hal Draper (1934), educational and study materials, bulletins, newspapers, pamphlets, convention materials,clippings, a membership manual, fliers and other printed ephemera, and a souvenir program from a 1960 reunion. Principal themes documented include relations between the YPSL and the Socialist Party USA (with which the YPSL was affiliated), political debate within the YPSL and within the Socialist Party, the influence of Trotskyism within the YPSL, and attitudes towards the Communist movement. There are also documents and printed ephemera from the Socialist Party's Youth Committee, The Workmen's Circle, and the Young Communist League. While the collection spans the years 1920-1964, the bulk of the material is from the 1930s.
Communism -- United States.; Socialism and youth -- United States.; Trotskyism -- United States.; Socialist Party (U.S.); Socialist Party (U.S.). Youth Committee; Young Communist League of the U.S.; Young People's Socialist League; Baker, Zachary M.
- Bergner, Donald: Forgery Charges and Expulsion, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Blast (Bronx YPSL Newspaper), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- City College: Flyers (Drafts), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings, 1935, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Communist Party Flyers and Pamphlets, undated, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Convention Handbook, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1933-1935, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Educational/Study Group Material, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Educational Department: Catalogs and Historical Booklets, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Falcon Call (Austrian Issue), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Falcon Guides Convention, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Finances (Bronx?), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Give Work to Youth" Campaign, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Greater New York YPSL: Convention Reports, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Greater New York YPSL: Executive Committee Statement, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Greater New York YPSL: Revolutionary Policy Committee, Proposed Program (H. Draper), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Leftwing of the YPSL (Bertman, Atkins, et al.): Defections to Workers Party, etc., 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Massachusetts YPSL: State Bulletin, Moscow Trials Issue, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Membership Manual, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- National Convention of the Young People's Socialist League in Cleveland, OH, July 23-24, 1932 (Box Shared Tamiment 069, Folder 9)
- National Student Bulletin, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- New York Spartacus Youth League: Anti-war Flyer, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Organizing Plans, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Rand School: Clarion Ad, 1920, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Rebel Songs, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Reports, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Reports, Minutes, Correspondence and Notes, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- SPUSA-YPSL Conflict (New York City), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- SPUSA Youth Committee: Correspondence, Reports and Minutes, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Socialist Unity Conference: Levy Group Proposal, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Structure: Proposal, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- United Front Committee for National Youth Day: YPSL Statement on, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Workmen's Circle: Meeting re: Heller-Geliebter, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Workmen's Circle: Petition from the National Fraternal Committee for Social Insurance, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Young Communist League: Flyers and Appeals to YPSL, undated, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Young Communist League: YPSL Statement on Splitting AFL Unions, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- YPSL Reunion (1st Annual): Souvenir Program, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Youth (Circle 8 Seniors, Bronx), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 37)